This morning,
I was in the Discord talking to a coach
from the United Kingdom
that's charging £30 an hour.
To any of my homies from other
countries, £30
is €35, it's $37.8
US,
and it's $58 Australian dollars.
I did my first personal training session
just over
10 years ago,
and that's what I started on.
And the biggest elephant in the room is
if you don't increase your prices over
time,
you become cheaper just through inflation
alone.
Everyone gets really excited about house
prices going up.
"Oh,
I made 100K on my house price." You
didn't. Your money is just worth less.
So it breaks my heart
that people out there
are charging not just what I charged 10
years ago, but significantly less.
Because I remember 10 years ago,
going to seminars where people
were saying 10
years before that,
the average rate of PT was £30.
Now, not all of you are personal trainers,
but a lot of you watching this are going
to be in service-based industries.
Maybe you're a physio,
maybe you're a yoga instructor,
maybe you're a coach, maybe
whatever it is.
You could even be a driving instructor.
Where the current model
is charging by the hour.
I'm going to break down some of the issues
with that, how to circumnavigate price
increases,
and break down some of the delusions
that you feed yourself as to
why it is that you can't increase your
price.
The biggest myth that's holding people
back about their hourly rate is location.
They seem to think that because London,
and New York, and Sydney, they
get Sydney prices and London prices,
that it is your distance to the
city that determines how much you charge.
That's just not true.
It is not where you live.
This lad in question that I
was chatting to said that he
lived 10 miles from Leeds, so therefore,
people couldn't afford to pay
more than that.
I even chased Uncle ChatGPT to find out
whether or not
this was just an illusion this guy
was force-feeding himself to put up with
the
fact he didn't want to go through the
discomfort of increasing his prices.
Leeds, apparently,
is the sixth richest city in the United
Kingdom.
And in 2015, it was reported there
were approximately 28,000
millionaires in the Yorkshire
and Humber region, which includes Leeds.
I'm not saying that all your clients have
to be millionaires.
I'm just saying there
are a lot more people with money than you
realize,
considering as a coach,
you actually only need between 10
and 20 clients.
If you had 10 clients that were wealthy,
that could see you three times a week,
that is your books full.
And you're probably thinking, "Oh,
but James, couldn't I
just have 30 clients
that all do one hour each?" Well, yeah,
kind of, but here's
another issue,
especially in the coaching realm.
If you have 30 clients seeing you for one
hour, you now need to manage 30 people.
Oh, Trish, oh, Sam, oh,
Delia can't come in until 2:00 PM.
I need to move her around.
When you only have 10 clients
that see you three times a
week, you only have to manage 10 people,
10 payments.
Not to mention, the people
that see you more frequently
are often the ones with the
larger disposable incomes,
and often they're the ones that
are more professional.
So when they cancel on you,
you might even say to them, "Oh,
do you know what, Sue?
You've given me six hours notice.
Don't worry about it." Then they message
you
going, "No, James, I'm messing you around.
I'll be offended if you don't charge me
for the session." Whereas the people that
are trying to save up pennies
and get a discount and nudge you on rate,
they expect
you to pay for it.
And here's a golden rule while I
was tangent on this because
this is a rifting video.
If someone doesn't show up to your
session, someone has
to pay for it. If you let them off,
you have to pay because it's money you're
not
earning. You were there. You were ready.
You're paying your rent in your gym
or whatever it is. You were there.
Someone has to pay for it. Now, of course,
the first couple of times, maybe let
them off. But if
that pattern starts to emerge,
they need to start paying for it.
And I would probably say if someone
was to miss four or five sessions in a
row,
sack them. Now,
it's not because you're a mean person
or you're trying to be
professional. It's more of a power trip.
The first time you sack a client,
it's like you put on that glove
that Thanos has
in "Avengers." You
are the most powerful person in the room.
People start whispering around in the gym.
They go, "Oh, you know what James did?
Came back from my Ibiza with a bit of a
comedown, sacked his clients.
One of them tried giving him lip,
paid him late, boom,
gone." Let me tell you this,
100% of all the headaches
that you have in your business come from
10% to
15% of your clients. If you sack them,
you now have 15% less
money and 100% less headaches. That
is a great deal.
So if it's not the geolocation of where
you're situated that's determining how
much
you get paid, what is it? Well,
quite simple, it's demand.
The more demand there
is for your services,
the more you can increase prices.
We see this on planes. Think about this.
If you wanted to fly from where you
are to Ibiza, it might be £100.
But if you want to go on a bank holiday
weekend, it's suddenly two
and a half times
that. Why?
Because fuel became more expensive,
the pilots wanted more money, the
planes suddenly be-- No.
Because more people want that route.
And if more people want that route at
that time, prices are going to go up.
Simple economics. Demand.
Apparently in the UK now,
you can get charged for
taking your kids out of school. Truancy.
But I believe some people have calculated
that even paying the school the fine of
taking the kids out, UK worries me.
Go to jail for a tweet.
It's still cheaper than trying to compete
with other people that want to go on the
bank holiday prices. But you get my drift.
And you will happily pay more to get
that flight on the bank holiday, be like,
"Oh,
it is the holidays." So why don't you see
that within your own business?
Now, there's only one time
that you can rationally lower your prices,
and that is
when your demand drops.
Say you get to December like it
is now at the recording of
this video.
You might have a few clients drop off
because Christmas is coming, or
financially or whatever it is.
When your books get quiet
and you're down to maybe
five clients, that
is a good time to maybe reduce prices
because there is not the
demand for your services. How do I know?
Because you're quiet.
The same sense goes that if you're full,
you are too cheap.
How do I know that you're full?
If you look at the busyness within your
business,
you can look at whether
that scale of pricing needs to go up
or down.
Some people out there
are charging a fortune for what they do,
but they've got fuck
all clients. They go, "Oh,
I just don't know how to get more
clients." And maybe
reduce prices. "Oh, but I've got a BSc
and I've got a
master's in kinesiology." I don't give a
fuck. No one gives a fuck.
I don't care if you went to uni for 10
years.
If there's no demand for your services,
you're going to have to drop your price.
So there is a time
and a place where you might reduce prices
to get busy, because
ultimately, you always want to be busy.
Because busyness makes you feel good,
it makes you feel like things
are going well,
and ultimately, the more people
that you're working with
and the more busy you are,
the more you're learning your trade,
the more you're understanding the people,
the
demographic, the avatar.
And for a lot of you
that want to go online and work
online, which you can do,
and I teach people to do,
the better you understand your
audience, the better.
Although looking back now, my first three,
four years on the
gym floor doing those slog long days
was some of the poorest paid
work I've ever done. In hindsight, it
was amazing because all of
that time on the
gym floor then allowed me to learn people
very well.
When I went online,
it paid back rather large dividends.
Now,
reducing your prices because you're not
busy is not the same as a discount.
Discounting can be at your peril.
It's one of the biggest mistakes
that people
make. They think, "Oh,
I haven't got enough clients.
I'm just going to do a flash sale,
25% off to get people through the door."
Unless
you're really struggling with demand
and there's nothing on the table
that you can
do to get more clients,
like going out flyering, asking for
referrals, pushing on social media,
hitting your email list.
If you're exhausted, sure. But
if you just need to work harder to get
sales,
dropping your price isn't the way to do
it.
And I'll explain it using this cleverly
positioned can of Nutonic.
So let's imagine this can of Nutonic
represents the amount of money
that you earn
for a session. Let's pretend this
is the amount Declan earns for being here
for this hour filming this.
Declan doesn't actually get to take home
all of
that money.
He doesn't get to take home all of the
liquid that's in the can because
Declan has costs. He has his car,
he has his rent,
he has his camera equipment, the
FX3 here with the ND filter, and the lens,
and the monitor, and
the HDMI cable, and all of these costs.
And the fact he eats a lot because he's a
young lad.
So actually,
out of the money he gets for the hour,
maybe let's say a third of it
is gone just in supporting Declan.
Then we could probably have a nuanced
opinion of what would be taxed, but this
isn't a tax video.
Then let's just say the top half of the
can.
Let's say from the pupil upwards
is Declan's take home.
The money he gets to go home and cherish,
and wave around in front of girls.
If he provides me a discount for this hour
out of generosity or because
he just wants to do a flash sale,
say he gives me a 25% discount,
that's a quarter
of the can,
which might just seem like a quarter.
But if we remember that his take home
is from the pupil upwards,
Declan giving me a
25% discount has actually halved the
amount of money he gets to take home,
because
that discount doesn't come out of his
costs.
By giving me a 25% discount,
it doesn't make his car finance cheaper,
it doesn't
make his rent cheaper,
it doesn't make the amount of food he eats
cheaper.
So when you do discount, it
is a big issue because the amount of cash
you have at
the end of the day
is significantly impacted.
Whereas if Declan could increase his
prices by 10%, 20% through creating
demand, through social media, prospecting,
whatever it is, all of that money is
going to be profit to him because your
costs don't go up when it comes to earning
more money. Your taxes do marginally,
but ultimately, if Declan was to squeeze
an extra $10 out of me rather than trying
to deduct $10, he would get to keep it.
It would have a massive impact on his
business.
This is why demand
is one of the biggest key factors you
should have.
Some of you will go spend three years at
university to earn your PhD in
kinesiology,
but you won't learn how to create demand
within your business, which,
trust me, pays you a lot more. So only
if you're desperate can you offer a
discount.
But you can't just throw it around
because, like I said, it's
significantly less money.
Even shaving 10% off your hourly rate
can be more of a 20% to 25% discount
if you think about the days of the
week.
That now means you've got to go into work
on a Saturday and work nearly a
full day to earn the same amount of money.
Whereas on the opposite, if you
were to increase your prices by 10%,
15% over the
next few months from watching
and absorbing this video on this channel
that you're
loving, I hope, that is all extra money,
which means you could actually have a half
day on a Thursday and a Friday
and still earn the same money
and have the afternoon
back to make more content,
write more emails,
be a social media strategist,
which then means you get more demand,
and then you put prices up more,
and then you
could... Anyway, you get the drift.
Now, another issue that this lad
was making is that he was charging £30 an
hour,
but then if you bought 10 sessions
or 20 sessions or 30 sessions, it became
cheaper and cheaper and cheaper. I said,
"Mate, at your best, you're earning less
than what people earned 10 years ago,
and at your worst, you're earning
significantly less." It shouldn't get
cheaper the more you hire someone.
Now, if you're charging for a service,
maybe like Netflix, Spotify, YouTube, you
might say to someone
that you give them a discount
if they purchase a year up
front. That's because
if you have an average customer duration
of, say, six months
within your business at a 10% markup,
if you're going to lock them in for 12
months, you now know
that you've doubled the amount
that you're going to earn from
that customer.
So if you give them a 25% discount,
you still work out in a better
position.
But that shouldn't be the same for you
charging an hourly rate.
It's going to be so much easier for you
guys just to have a flat hourly rate.
Your dentist doesn't charge you less
if you have a checkup every three months
instead of six months. Your car mechanic,
your hairdresser.
Some barbers might give you a discount,
but that's because they don't understand
what they're doing either.
Every single place you go to in life.
If you've been driving a lot more than
usual, you don't walk into the petrol
station and go,
"Can I get my petrol a bit cheaper because
I've done more miles?"
It doesn't work like that. There
is a flat price for things,
and they're going to
move up and down based on demand
or conflicts that
are happening in the Middle East
or Europe, whatever.
My dad's always raving on, "Oh,
the drum of oil has gone up by
$3." Don't care.
So for all of you watching this,
whatever it is that you're
working in, have a flat hourly rate,
because then when you do want to put your
prices up,
you just put the flat hourly rate up.
And when you're getting a bit quieter,
you can bring that flat hourly rate down.
But ultimately, those of you
that use social media properly should
never have to
discount your hourly rate.
Which brings me on to kind of a secondary
rule on that.
You can discount a product
but never a service.
We have a margin on Nutonic, so therefore,
if we want to run a Black Friday
discount,
which we're going to do next week,
I think, we can just say, "Hey,
instead of making 20% a can,
we're going to make 10%," and that's fine.
But if you're in a service-based industry,
whether a masseuse, a yoga instructor, a
hairdresser, whatever,
if you discount a service,
like I said before, you're now
having to just do more work
and more hours and more time in the
business to earn
the same amount of money.
It's going to be Black Friday very,
very soon.
For those of you that
are in a service-based industry,
you're not going to have
really anything you can sell.
But it's cool.
We'll work over the next 12 months
together.
I'll keep pumping out content on this
channel, and we can create some kind of
product and offering
that you can put out
that you could discount.
Now,
one of the biggest rebuttals people get
when they're increasing their prices
is, "Oh, but my clients.
I love my clients." And there
was once a guy I used to
train called Russell in the UK, and he
was a bit of a hard nut.
He scared me a little bit. He also
was a bit of a show-off.
He would pull up in his Rolls-Royce,
or it was a Bentley, I can't remember,
and he
would, "Oh,
I've accidentally left my £20,000 watch
on.
Silly me." But he would always haggle me
on price.
It's a bit weird for someone to flex about
their wealth and haggle you on price.
And I remember I said to him,
"I'm putting up my prices." He goes,
"Not for me,
you're not." He goes,
"I see you two times a week." I go,
"It doesn't change the
fact that I'm busy. If anything,
you're part of the problem,
not the solution." And
I said to him over two weeks, I said,
"I'm putting the prices up because I'm not
paying it." I said,
paying it." So
eventually I said, "Do you know what?
Our session just went from an hour to 45
minutes." He goes, "Fine." He goes, "I'll
do my own warm-up." And that was that.
If someone can't afford your full hourly
rate, get them to come see you for half an
hour. I did this quite a lot.
I took my hourly rate across two
and a half years
from £30 an hour to £55 an hour.
And for all the people
that couldn't afford it, we
just did shorter sessions. Now,
if you're a masseuse, sure,
it means 15 minutes
less massage. If you're a hairdresser,
maybe they're doing their own beard trim
or
whatever it is, or a barber. But
if someone won't move on price,
you just need to
move on hours. Now, the good news here
was when I increased my hourly rate to
£55,
I said, "Cool, half-hour sessions
are £30." So that means for £60 a week,
someone could see me on a Monday
and a Thursday.
I'd write their program for both the
sessions.
For £60, they're getting two sessions.
I would then say, "Do your own warm-up,
come to me ready to train." They'd walk
through the door.
I would take them through the hardest part
of the workout,
whether it's squats, split squats,
bench press, whatever it was.
Then when the time ran out, I didn't say,
"You're going home." I said, "Go train
your arms, your delts,
your glutes," whatever it is,
and they could do it.
So if someone's not willing to go up on
price,
come down on the amount of time that
you give them. Now,
if people genuinely can't afford you,
that's fine.
That's really okay.
Keep marketing so you can find more people
that can.
Now,
people that train with you for a while
and then say, "Oh, just can't afford it
anymore," that is bullshit.
People can always find a way to afford a
night out and
some designer clothes.
If they're saying that, the truth
is they don't value what
you're offering them anymore. So
if you have a lot of clients
that start working
with you,
then after a short period of time start
going, "Oh, just can't afford
it", your offering is just dog shit,
and you need to work on that.
Same way,
if you get people asking for a refund
or people dropping off in the first
few months,
that's just a big indicator
that you need to improve the quality of
your service or the results
that you give people.
A lot of you watching this video will
probably wanna move online, start working
online, start working remote,
opening your laptop in Bali
and being a digital
nomad, which is cool.
And you might not know what to charge.
Now, my advice to people
that I teach in my mentorship, oh,
link in description,
dirty dog,
is to start with the amount
that you charge for an hour
and translating
that to a week.
Because the majority of people you onboard
for your online offering
should be serviceable in an hour. Now,
what if you like writing
intricate programmings of undulating
periodization?
Or what if you're someone
that does something online for someone
like
complex accounting and you're like, "Oh,
this is gonna take more than that." Cool.
Often when you work with people online,
the onboarding process is the most
time-taxing. But then over time,
people become more self-efficient.
So even if they take an hour
and a half in your first week
and you technically take
a loss,
four or five weeks into training someone
online, it's a check-in, it's a
program rotation, it's a how you doing,
and you just got £55 to chat to someone
for
six minutes across three days,
which significantly increases your hourly
rate.
Then guess what? Over time, set a cap.
For online coaching,
probably 60 clients
is gonna be the absolute limit.
After that,
you're just gonna see a reduction in your
quality of service.
Same way for personal trainers.
They can do about 30 hours a week before
they start
to dip. Barbers,
you might get more because you can kind of
zone out and just do a
fade. But doing stuff like PT
and where you're walking around in the
gym, moving
weights, it's exhausting.
So I know a lot of you
that work online aren't sure about
when to charge people. Do you do monthly,
12 weeks, six months up
front?
Although it's appealing to get loads of
money from people up front, often
you are just increasing the barrier to
entry.
Imagine everyone
that wants to do business with you has to
jump a wall to do it.
For many of you, you're just making
that wall massive and really difficult and
wondering why no one's joining your
program.
Even my course that I'm promoting down in
the links below.
Sure, the full course costs this,
but I have a short-form content mastery
course
that costs a tenth as much.
I am creating a smaller wall
that they can jump over
and when they get to the other side,
they go, "Jesus Christ, this
is better than I
thought." Then they're more likely to go
to the effort necessary to jump the next
wall. Things like personal training
and barbering, yoga, masseuse, are often
seen in people's minds as a weekly cost.
So I often like telling people in the
online coaching space to try and charge
weekly because it mimics the same thing
you would have done with people.
If you had a PT, you see them once,
twice a week.
Often people will come in
and just give you a bit of cash.
They may want to pay up front. Cool.
If they want to pay up front,
that's great.
But for some people,
they kind of just want to pay you for the
shortest period of
time necessary to see whether
or not it's shit.
And if it's not, they'll stay, and
if it is, they're gone.
And ultimately, for the majority of you,
you just need to lower that wall as low as
possible. And guess what?
If someone joins, gets their program,
and fucks off after
a week, yeah, that's shit,
but the most people online don't do that.
And if they do do that a lot, it's often,
again, a sign of the level of your
coaching or offering. Some people
are adamant that you need to bill for
three
months up front.
You're just saying to someone,
"You've got to give me a load of
money." The risk is then on the person,
not yourself.
Because one of you has to have the risk.
Now,
if you say it's three months up front,
if you have a lot of demand, you can do
that.
But if you haven't got a lot of demand for
your services, like I say, it's
just making it unnecessarily difficult.
So take the risk from them having it to
you having it and just say, "Look,
fortnightly, weekly,
pay for two weeks up front," whatever it
is.
Then you at least get your time,
write in the program for that person.
And even if they do bum you,
they take the program and do a runner.
Let's say Steve joins.
Four-day split muscle growth between 20,
let's say
he's 28. You write his program, he leaves,
and you go, "Goddammit, Steve only gave
me £55, and I wrote his program,
and I really worked really hard for that,
and I'm really disappointed
and depressed because he just
left after week one.
I can't believe it." Well, guess what?
In two weeks' time, Billy's gonna join,
and he's only 32, and he's got the same
goals. You get Steve's program,
you change the name to Billy,
and you give it to
flipping Steve,
and he's gonna flipping love it.
And even though I just got Steve
and Billy the wrong way around,
you get the drift.
As an online coach, the majority of you,
you're gonna have a branch of, I don't
know, like 40 programs.
And then as soon as someone joins
and you get to know them,
you know which one's perfect for them.
And you go, "Oh,
this sounds just like Trisha." You send
them Trisha's program.
Oh, you don't have a leg press.
You change it, and now Sandra
is the new one.
So when someone comes again and says,
"Hey, I do this.
I haven't got a leg press." You go, "Cool,
get Sandra's." So billing for three
months can be pretty stupid.
And commitment periods in general just
make you look
like a beggy little twat. "Oh,
you must stay with me for three months.
You're locked in.
You're locked in." Imagine going on a date
with someone and they
go, "Look, if we're gonna go for dinner,
I must have a commitment from you that you
will not go for dinner with anyone else
for three months, okay?
There is no other dating.
I need you to delete Hinge now." You're
like, "We just
met. You're mental.
Get in the way." Just be chilled.
The more chilled you can be, the better.
And the commitment periods
are kind of bullshit anyway because all of
you should be
offering a money-back guarantee,
which I have another video for on this
channel.
But the closing remarks on this will be
that pricing, although a very complex
subject,
is tantamount to you guys operating
and running a good business.
You do not want to be cheap.
You want to be the most expensive
possible.
Because imagine this as a scenario.
You wake up this morning,
your iPhone's dead Your charger's let you
down.
It's done a dirty. Overnight,
it's just died.
So now your alarm didn't go off,
you're late to work.
Your boss was going to give you a pay
rise, not anymore. You missed training.
You haven't got time for breakfast,
you're hungry.
It's the worst day of your life.
You go on Amazon, think,
"I'll have to get myself a new cable for
my iPhone."
There's four available, one for £4,
one for £6, one for £7,
and one for £19.99. Now, at first you go,
"Jesus Christ.
Expensive for an iPhone cable."
But you go, "Do you know what?
This is important to me." Because
if you go cheap twice and it lets you down
again in two weeks' time,
you'll be so angry with yourself.
But you know that one for £19.99 wouldn't
be that expensive unless it was good.
You don't want to be let down again,
so you go for the good one
and it doesn't let
you down. You want the best, bit like me.
I just bought a Porsche 911.
I don't know much of the difference
between them, Carrera, 4S, Targa,
so I just got the most expensive one.
Not the GT3 RS. I don't made of money.
I'm not so wealthy. I just got the GT3.
Why? Because it's the best.
How do I know? I could tell by the prices.
Oh,
but there's this 911 that's half the
price. It's probably half the car.
Don't attract cheap because you just
attract people like the iPhone cable that
don't take you seriously and
are more likely to let you down.
If anything,
the more expensive you become,
the better your clients are.
I just recently moved my one-hour calls in
my mentorship to
$1,000, which is to me, insane.
I'm not going to lie to you, the level and
quality of the conversations has got so
much better.
Also, I had to move someone the other day.
The $1,000 an hour people are like, "Yeah,
fine.
Whatever." Whereas sometimes you have
people, when you charge less,
who moan about
it. It's crazy. People
are nicer in business class than they
are in economy.
They're even nicer in first class.
Not all the time,
the majority of the time.
The best clients you want in the world,
people that are just happy to pay.
If you generate demand, everything,
everything becomes easier.
I have a coach that I use online.
I don't even have his phone number.
Barely chat to him.
He sends me all my programs.
I do it on a spreadsheet.
I've got one of the world's most advanced
training apps in the world and I'm doing
my workouts out of a spreadsheet.
He tells me what to do, I get it done.
If I don't train for two weeks,
I don't ask for my money back.
I'm getting good results from the
training. I'm not bothered.
Why do I pay him so much?
Because he's good at what he does.
So there's some lessons
that you need to understand about pricing.
You don't just have an hourly rate based
on where you live.
There's so much more things complex to
that.
Building demand for your business
is kind of what I specialize in.
Now, I can't be sure what YouTube
is going to put right here,
but I guarantee it's
a video that you're going to enjoy
and learn from.
So head over to that video
if you found this one useful, and enjoy.
Bye.